Guide to the RIDGE Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
RIDGE records
1923-2015
1987-2014
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6295
6295-001
RIDGE (Organization)
9.66 cubic feet 10 boxes, 2 oversize folders, 4 tubes, 39 CD-roms, 1 DVD, 8 videocassettes
Records of RIDGE, a Roslyn-based community organization focused on environmental and land use activism in Upper Kittitas County, Washington from 1988 until 2014. Records in the collection include litigation material related to the development of the Suncadia Resort, RIDGE office files, newspaper clippings documenting RIDGE’s projects and activism, land use maps, and RIDGE promotional material.
RIDGE was a community organization in Roslyn, Washington formed in 1988. Ellie Belew and Douglas Kilgore were leaders of the organization, which engaged in activism around forestry and land use issues during the late 1980s and into the early 2010s. RIDGE partnered with labor groups-- especially the building trades unions-- in a long fight to block the development of what is now the Suncadia Resort, the first Master Planned Resort in Washington State. Master Planned Resort [MPR] is a type of zoning distinction defined by the Washington State Growth Management [GMA] Act. MPRs are self-contained and fully integrated planned unit developments, in a setting of significant natural amenities, with primary focus on destination resort facilities consisting of short-term visitor accommodations associated with a range of developed on-site indoor or outdoor recreational facilities. The plan allows urban development outside of urban areas and connection to municipal wastewater connections but requires the MPR to be separated from surrounding communities.
RIDGE used a variety of tactics to attempt to block Suncadia’s development including: litigation, land use mapping, water rights, community meetings, and zoning changes. Later, RIDGE engaged with Futurewise to litigate and organize for reforms to the Kittitas County Comprehensive Plan. RIDGE dissolved in 2014.
RIDGE members warned of the negative environmental and economic effects typical of the boom and bust cycles of logging on local economies. The boom and bust cycle of a town dominated by a major extractive industry was a familiar cycle in Roslyn, founded in 1886 as a mining company town initiated and platted by the Northern Pacific Coal Company, a subsidiary of the Northern Pacific Railway. The last mine closed in Roslyn in 1963, and the bust contributed to an economic downturn and population decline. After the loss of mining jobs, the town’s demographics were largely composed of retired mining families and older white people who moved to Roslyn to complete tree-planting contracts.
RIDGE’s connection to labor organizing is unique among other environmental groups of the time. RIDGE challenged the notion that extractive economy workers and environmentalists have competing interests, and instead sought to harmonize the need for a sustainable forest economy among workers and those concerned with the environment. RIDGE joined a coalition with the building trades unions after Suncadia expressed interest in bringing in open shop contractors to build the resort and that they had no intention of utilizing a responsible contract. Once it was evident Suncadia was going to be built despite efforts to block the development, the coalition fought for and obtained a pledge for employing union workers in its construction. The organization’s leaders also have strong ties with the labor movement. Doug Kilgore is connected to the labor movement in Washington State, and Ellie Belew has researched and authored several books in collaboration with labor unions and labor activists.
Timeline of RIDGE’s History:
Spring 1988: Cle Elum Chamber of Commerce hosts community meetings about the future of Upper Kittitas County, and land use and sustainable forestry emerge as a community concern
Summer 1988: RIDGE founded by school teachers Doug Johnson and Susan Willis Johnson with a goal to build a sustainable forest economy and ecosystem
Fall 1988: RIDGE learns Plum Creek Timber Company plans to log approximately 15,000 acres of timber near Roslyn, Washington
Winter 1988: Doug Kilgore and Ellie Belew join RIDGE
February 1989: RIDGE presents concerns about overcutting in the Yakima Basin to the Forest Practices Board [FPB]
October 1989: RIDGE facilitates first state-wide coalition meeting to discuss overcutting on private forest lands
1988-1989: RIDGE hosts community meetings, gathers signatures to oppose Plum Creek’s logging plans
1989-1990: RIDGE participates in Sustainable Forestry Roundtable [SFR] and SFR subcommittees
Fall 1990: RIDGE formally appeals logging plans in L.T. Murray Recreation Area and focuses on documenting side-by-side land parcels in L.T. Murray and how the cumulative effects of logging are not accounted for in Forest Practices Applications
Fall 1990: SFR does not reach consensus for proposing legislative package to Washington State Legislature
1990: Growth Management Act [GMA] passes in Washington State Legislature, Kittitas County adopts GMA
Early 1990s: Previously logged land parcels in Upper Kittitas County are proposed for development. RIDGE expands focus to include broader land use focus and uses GMA and other planning regulations to advocate for zoning designations of resource lands of long-term commercial significance
1992: Appeals process for L.T. Murray Recreation Area ends, and the area changes from private logging to public management
1992-1995: RIDGE appeals Plum Creek Timber Company’s application for Washington State’s first Master Planned Resort [MPR]
April 3 1995: 14,000 acres of forest land in Upper Kittitas County are declared resource lands of long-term commercial significance by Growth Management Hearings Board for Eastern Washington
1996: Plum Creek Timber Company sells 7,600 acres of land to Trendwest Resorts for development of MPR
Mid-to-late 1990s: RIDGE rallies community members to identify potential impacts to human and natural communities if MPR is developed
April - September 2001: RIDGE and Trendwest (now Suncadia) engage in litigation to mitigate effects of MPR on surrounding communities and agree upon Settlement Agreement for MPR
2001 - 2008: RIDGE enforces and monitors Settlement Agreement. Four amendments added to agreement and Suncadia attempts to dissolve agreement through legal processes
2009: Several RIDGE board members form a new community group called R-Town
December 8 2009: RIDGE and Suncadia go to court over enforcement of the Settlement Agreement’s terms
July 15, 2013: Kittitas County Judge Scott R. Sparks terminates the Settlement Agreement and all remaining claims
August 5, 2013: RIDGE announces no further plans to pursue an appeal
2014: RIDGE dissolves
Source: https://www.blackpast.org/african-american-history/roslyn-washington/
Source: https://web.archive.org/web/20170314072214/http://www.roslynridge.org/history.php
Source: https://app.leg.wa.gov/rcw/default.aspx?cite=36.70a.360
The collection has been arranged into the following series and subseries
SERIES 1: LAND TRUSTS, 1997-2008
Subseries A: Projects, 1997-2008
Subseries B: Standards and Practices, 2000-2007
SERIES 2: RIDGE OFFICE FILES, 1989-2015
Subseries A: Educational and Training Material, 2004-2008
Subseries B: Meeting Minutes and Notes, 1989-2015
Subseries C: Correspondence and Newsletters, 1989-2010
Subseries D: RIDGE Organizational History, 1989-2001
Subseries E: Promotional Material, Website, and Meeting Notices, 1992-2014
Subseries F: Maps, Trails, and Directions, 2000-2008
SERIES 3: SUSTAINABLE FORESTRY AND LAND USE, 1938, 1980-2013
Subseries A: Sustainable Forestry Working Groups and Coalitions, 1987-2000
Subseries B: Kittitas County and Kittitas City Planning and Politics, 1994-2009
Subseries C: Water and Sewerage Project Materials, 1985-2013
Subseries D: Newspaper Clippings Regarding Floods, Droughts, and Land Use, 1990-2009
Subseries E: Land Use Proposals and Applications, 1938, 1980-2009
Subseries F: Oversize Maps, 1986-2013
SERIES 4: NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS, PROMOTIONAL MATERIAL AND PRESS, 1977, 1984-2009
Subseries A: RIDGE, 1977, 1984-2009
Subseries B: Suncadia/Trendwest and Plum Creek Timber Company, 1994-2006
SERIES 5: GRANTS, NONPROFIT, AND INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE [IRS] DOCUMENTS, 1988-2015
Subseries A: General, 1988-2015
Subseries B: RIDGE Dissolution, 2009-2014
SERIES 6: RIDGE/SUNCADIA LITIGATION, 1923, 1988-2013
Subseries A: RIDGE Contract Advice, 2007-2011
Subseries B: Compliance Contract Auditing, 2005-2008
Subseries C: Settlement Drafts, Agreements, Amendments, and Easements, 1991-2010
Subseries D: Correspondence, 1923, 1993-2009
Suberies E: Negotiation and Proposals, 1988-2007
Subseries F: General Suncadia Files, 1999-2013
SERIES 7: AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL, 1984-2014
This collection contains the organizational records of RIDGE during their years of operation from 1988 to 2014. Records include litigation files and other assorted materials regarding the development of the Suncadia Resort; lawsuit materials; RIDGE office files; RIDGE promotional materials, including newsletters and flyers; correspondence; oversize land use maps; photographs; news clippings and media coverage; contract drafts and contract negotiation notes; and several videocassettes. The records are mostly paper-based, but also include a large number of CD-roms containing additional digital files.
See the arrangement note in the administrative information section for a detailed list of series and subseries. More detailed scope and content information is also included at the series level in the box/folder inventory.
This collection contains references to the Yakama Nation. In the mid 1990s, the Yakama Nation renamed itself from “Yakima” to “Yakama” to more closely represent pronunciation in their native language. All mentions of the Yakama Nation in this collection have been updated to reflect this change in spelling, though original documents may still have the outdated spelling, depending on the age of the materials.
Source: http://www.yakamanation-nsn.gov/history3.php
Web crawls of RIDGE’s former website, roslynridge.org, can be found on the Wayback Machine’s internet archive.
No restrictions on access for paper-based materials. VHS cassettes and CDs are closed until processed. No user access copy is available for material on VHS or CDs. Users may be able to obtain a reproduction of the media for a fee. Contact Special Collections for more information.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
Donated by Douglas Kilgore and Ellie Belew.
RIDGE (Organization)$vArchives; RIDGE (Organization)$xPress coverage; Suncadia (Resort)$xHistory$vSources; Environmentalism$zWashington (State); Conservation of natural resources$zWashington (State); Forest conservation$zWashington (State); Land use$zWashington (State); Labor$zWashington (State); Labor unions$zWashington (State); Labor movement$zWashington (State); Johnson, Douglas A..$d1948-; Johnson, Susan Willis; Belew, Ellie; Kilgore, Douglas H.; Business correspondence; Minutes (Records); Contracts; Maps; Photographs; Aerial photographs; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Environmental Activism; Forestry and Forestry Products; Labor History; Washington (State)
- LAND TRUSTS, 1997-2008; SERIES 1 (Box-folder 1/1-8, 3/2-4, 4/24)
  Land trust project material including maps, notes, correspondence, easements, and land trust standards and practices. Additional material related to conservation easements can be found in SERIES 6: RIDGE/SUNCADIA LITIGATION.
  - Projects, 1997-2008; Subseries A (Box-folder 1/1-2, 1/4, 1/6-8, 3/2-4, 4/24)
    - Roslyn Ridge Project: Map, Notes, Articles, and Correspondence, 2005-2008 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - The Cascade Agenda and Kittitas Land Conservancy: Correspondence, Notes, Publications, and Maps with Transparency, 2005-2008 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Conservation Trust Materials Concerning Development of Trendwest Resorts, Sapphire Skies, and Cle Elum, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Mountains to Sound Greenway Trust and Kittitas Caucus, 2004 November 15 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Mountains to Sound Greenway Trust, Correspondence from Ken Konigsmark to Ellie Belew, 2001 Report to Donors, Meeting Notes, 1999 November 23-2001 October 1 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Correspondence and Draft Proposal for Ridge to River Land Trust, approximately 2000 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Kittitas Conservation Trust Phase 2, Grant of Conservation Easement, 2007 March 23 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Kittitas Conservation Trust Stream C Corridor Grant of Conservation Easement (1 of 2), 2004 October 8-2007 January 16 (Box-folder 3/3)
      Stream C Corridor was a parcel of land included in the RIDGE Settlement Agreement that was subject to conservation easements and other protection from development. After the termination of the RIDGE Settlement Agreement, Stream C and other parcels of land were taken out of protection and are being built upon as of 2020.
    - Kittitas Conservation Trust Stream C Corridor Grant of Conservation Easement (2 of 2), 2004 October 8-2007 January 16 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Ridge to River Land Trust Draft and Position Paper by Douglas Kilgore, approximately 1997-1998 (Box-folder 4/24)
  - Standards and Practices, 2000-2007; Subseries B (Box-folder 1/3, 1/5)
    - Newspaper Articles, Notes, Correspondence, Fundraising Materials, and Land Trust Pamphlet, 2000-2005 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Publications and Assorted Material Regarding Land Trust Standards and Practices, Land Conservation Options for Landowners in Kittitas County, Washington, 2004-2007 (Box-folder 1/5)
      Contains draft deed of conservation easement on Cascade Land Conservancy
- RIDGE OFFICE FILES, 1989-2015; SERIES 2 (Box-folder 1/11-13, 2/9-10, 2/14-16, 2/30-31, 2/37-39, 3/8, 4/26-27, 5/2-4, 5/6, 5/12, 5/15-17, 5/19, 5/21, 5/31, 7/5-9, 7/16-22, 8/1, 8/7, 8/9-11, 8/13-14, 8/21-22, 8/36, 9/1, 10)
  Educational and training material, meeting minutes, notes, correspondence, newsletters, promotional material, news clippings and press, organizational history, promotional materials, website documentation and updates, meeting notices, trails and directions. Oversize maps, oversize newsprint, and electronic records appear throughout this series. More news clippings and press regarding RIDGE can be found in SERIES 4: NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS, PROMOTIONAL MATERIAL, AND PRESS. More material related to RIDGE organizational records can be found in SERIES 5: GRANTS, NONPROFIT, AND INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE [IRS] DOCUMENTS.
  - Educational and Training Material, 2004-2008; Subseries A (Box-folder 1/11, 1/13, 7/9)
    - John E. Perkins Consensus Governance Workshop Handouts, 2008 May 17-18 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Subcommittee and Consensus Training Materials, Including Booklet "Get Off the Dime" by John E. Perkins, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Assessment and Training Exercises and Open Space Trail Tour Planning, 2004 July 8-2005 July 19 (Box-folder 7/9)
  - Meeting Minutes and Notes, 1989-2015; Subseries B (Box-folder 1/12, 2/37, 3/8, 5/15, 5/31, 7/5-8, 7/19-20, 8/7, 8/13-14, 8/36, 10)
    - Meetings with Consultant Sam Collins, approximately 2003-2004 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Assorted RIDGE Business Notes, approximately 2013 (Box-folder 2/37)
    - RIDGE Board Meeting Agenda, 2009 February 10-26 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Statewide Meeting Minutes, Agenda, Mailing Lists, Notes, and Political Action Committee Information, 1989 October 21 (Box-folder 5/15)
    - RIDGE Meeting Minutes and Assorted Materials, 2000 July 3-approximately 2015 (Box-folder 5/31)
      Contains Roslyn City Council resolution for forest stewardship, Suncadia lawsuit material, and developers' resort development plan
    - Notes, Meeting Minutes, Promotional Material, Public Notices, Kittitas County Development Services Materials, and Assorted Material (1 of 4), 1999-2006 (Box-folder 7/5)
      Contains transmittal memorandum from Suncadia and memoranda related to Kittitas County Community Development Services
    - Notes, Meeting Minutes, Promotional Material, Public Notices, Kittitas County Development Services Materials, and Assorted Material (2 of 4), 1999-2006 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Notes, Meeting Minutes, Promotional Material, Public Notices, Kittitas County Development Services Materials, and Assorted Material (3 of 4), 1999-2006 (Box-folder 7/7)
      Contains planning commission findings and comprehensive plan map
    - Notes, Meeting Minutes, Promotional Material, Public Notices, Kittitas County Development Services Materials, and Assorted Material (4 of 4), 1999-2006 (Box-folder 7/8)
      Contains planning committee executive statement
    - General Suncadia Meeting, Agenda, Correspondence, and Newspaper Clippings, 2006 October 23-December 2 (Box-folder 7/19)
    - Meeting Notes, Correspondence, Memos, Maps, and Kittitas Department of Labor and Industries Wage List, 2005 July 29-2006 July 7 (Box-folder 7/20)
      Contains oversize newsprint
    - Community Notices, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Notes, and Material from Roslyn City Council and Kittitas County, 2002 March 6-2005 December 6 (Box-folder 8/7)
      Contains CD-rom and oversize newsprint
    - Minutes, Notes, and Newspaper Clipping, 2004 April 19-2006 April 16 (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Notices, Minutes, Notes, Correspondence, and Plat Maps, 2003 July 1-2008 November (Box-folder 8/14)
      Contains oversize map
    - RIDGE Meeting Notes, Maps, Correspondence, 2002 February 19-2003 May 21 (Box-folder 8/36)
    - CD 17-19: RIDGE Documentation: Maps, Report Booklets, Master Planned Resort [MPR], and Urban Growth Area [UGA], 2014 April 22-October 3 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and Newsletters, 1989-2010; Subseries C (Box-folder 2/9-10, 2/14, 2/16, 2/30, 4/26-27, 5/2-3, 5/16-17, 8/10)
    - Fund Letters, 1998 November-1999 May (Box-folder 2/9)
    - RIDGE Line Newsletter, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Newsletters, 2000 October 25-2003 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Newspaper Clippings, RIDGE Line Newsletters, Flyers, and RIDGE Position Paper on RIDGE Settlement Agreement, 1997 December 4-2007 July 15 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Mailing List and Contacts, 2009 January 22-2010 November 27 (Box-folder 2/30)
      Contains CD-roms
    - RIDGE Fundraising Letter, 1991 February 11 (Box-folder 4/26)
    - David D. Kinghorn Memorial Communication, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 4/27)
    - Assorted Correspondence from RIDGE Treasurer Jim Fisk, 1992 February 28-1993 February 28 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Estate of Gary I. Parson, 2001 April 12-June 14 (Box-folder 5/3)
      Gary I. Parson included RIDGE in his estate
    - Newsletters, Correspondence, and Newspaper Clippings, 1993 April-1995 May (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Correspondence from Jeffrey Jacobs to Susan WIllis Johnson and Doug Kilgore and Partial Copy of Jeffrey Jacobs' "New Pioneers", Chapter 8 "Save Roslyn Ridge", 1993 May 15-1996 January 2 (Box-folder 5/17)
    - RIDGE Line Quarterly Newsletter, 2008 (Box-folder 8/10)
  - RIDGE Organizational History, 1989-2001; Subseries D (Box-folder 5/6, 5/12, 5/21)
    - Draft of New Plan for Organizational Structure of RIDGE, approximately 2001 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Community Meeting Agenda, History, and Talking Points, 1990 November 19-20 (Box-folder 5/12)
      Contains material about forest management
    - Notes and Historical Information about RIDGE, approximately 1989-1992 (Box-folder 5/21)
  - Promotional Material, Website, and Meeting Notices, 1992-2014; Subseries E (Box-folder 2/15, 2/31, 2/38-39, 5/4, 5/19, 8/21-22, 9/1)
    - RIDGE Meeting Notices, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, and Assorted Material, 1993 April 17-June 18 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Ridge Website Transfer: Notes, Notices, and Correspondence, 2013 August 12-2014 June 30 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - RIDGE Website Updates: Design and Related Documentation, 2008 October-2011 November (Box-folder 2/38)
    - RIDGE Website Updates: Design and Related Documentation, 2006 June 12-2009 December 15 (Box-folder 2/39)
    - Fundraising Materials for RIDGE, 1992 February 16-1994 (Box-folder 5/4)
      Contains Susan Willis Johnson letter to Northern Kittitas County Tribune
    - New Member Packet, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 5/19)
    - Douglas Kilgore and Ellie Belew's World Affairs Council Presentation, 2009 September 29 (Box-folder 8/21)
    - Postcards, Handouts, Reports, Maps, RIDGE Line Newsletters, Washington Environmental Council "Voices" Newsletter, 2002 July 23-2005 October 25 (Box-folder 8/22)
    - RIDGE Leaflets, approximately 1994 January 31-2008 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Trails, Maps, and Directions, 2000-2008; Subseries F (Box-folder 7/16-18, 7/21-22, 8/1, 8/9, 8/11)
    - Trails, 2003 January 3-2008 May 16 (Box-folder 7/16)
      Contains oversize maps
    - Suncadia Phase Maps, 2005 (Box-folder 7/17)
    - Assorted Onsite Suncadia Mapping, approximately 2003 (Box-folder 7/18)
    - Trailhead Interpreter Center, 2004 June 27 (Box-folder 7/21)
    - Trails and MountainStar Master Planned Resort [MPR], 2000 October-2007 August 12 (Box-folder 7/22)
      Contains CD-roms and oversize maps
    - State Route 903 Spur, RIDGE Line Newsletter, Meeting Sign-in List, and List of Adjacent Property Owners, 2004-2008 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Driving Tour Directions and Maps for Roslyn Ridge Area, 2006 April 15 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Directions from Suncadia to Roslyn, Washington, approximately 2008 (Box-folder 8/11)
- SUSTAINABLE FORESTRY AND LAND USE, 1938, 1980-2013; 1980-2013; SERIES 3 (Box-folder 1/14-27, 2/33, 3/5-7, 4/4-11, 4/13-16, 4/18-22, 5/1, 5/7-9, 5/11, 5/13-14, 5/18, 5/32, 8/2-6, 8/8, 8/16-17, 8/29-32, 9/2-5, 10, OS Folder 1-2, Tube 1-3, Tube 5)
  Material related to sustainable forestry working groups and coalitions, Kittitas County and Kittitas City planning and politics, water and sewerage projects, news clippings and press, and land use proposals, plans, and applications. Types of material include notes, charts, photographs, correspondence, legal documents, reports, meeting minutes, and Washington State Legislative bills. Oversize maps, oversize newsprint, and electronic records appear throughout this series. More information related to land use on the site of Suncadia Resort can be found in SUBSERIES 6: RIDGE/SUNCADIA LITIGATION.
  RIDGE participated in the Sustainable Forestry Roundtable [SFR] and various SFR subcommittees from 1989-1990. SFR sought to create a legislative package through consensus of all participating groups and propose legislation to state lawmakers. SFR was unable to achieve consensus when RIDGE and several national and local Audubon Society chapters rejected the legislative packet because of its lack of coverage of sustainable forestry and forest rates of harvest.
  RIDGE monitored and mapped forestry practices in L.T. Murray Recreation Area managed by the Department of Wildlife from 1990 to 1992. RIDGE did this to demonstrate how Forest Practice Applications did not take into account cuts in side-by-side locations of forested areas by using Kittitas County’s recently-adopted Washington State’s Growth Management Act [GMA], other planning regulations, and legal action to advocate for designating traditional forest, mining, and agricultural lands as “resource lands of long-term commercial significance”. RIDGE advocated for zoning and other land use regulations and policies that supported their goal of a sustainable forest economy. The appeal for logging plans they filed in L.T. Murray is sometimes called “The Hitchcock Case” in some records in the collection.
  Source: https://web.archive.org/web/20160420143053/http://www.roslynridge.org/history.php
  - Sustainable Forestry Working Groups and Coalitions, 1987-2000; Subseries A (Box-folder 4/13-16, 4/18-22, 5/7, 5/9, 5/11, 5/14)